<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Photonics Spotlight</title>
<description>Blog articles on topics in photonics, particularly laser technology and application.</description>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight.html?s=rss</link>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>RP Photonics Consulting GmbH, 2018</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 13:35:35 +0100</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<title>The Relevance of Photonics Buyer's Guides for Users and Advertisers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_11_19.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is discussed in which ways buyers guides in the area of photonics are relevant for users (buyers) and for suppliers (advertisers). Also, practical criteria for selecting a suitable resource are given. Further, the article explains important fundamental aspects of branding and lead generation.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 12:14:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_11_19.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Resonator Modes in Microchip Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_09_28.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is explained how the resonator modes of a microchip laser are formed by thermal lensing effects. Some example cases are analyzed, showing that the concept works well for a 1-W laser, while beam quality will be lost for substantially higher power levels.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2018 17:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_09_28.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>What is Different for Quasi-Three-Level Lasers?</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_08_22.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Compared with four-level gain media, quasi-three-level gain media behave differently in many respects. It is important to understand which statements on four-level lasers are also valid for three-level lasers, and which laser simulation software can be used for them.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 09:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_08_22.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thoughts on Thermal Lensing</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_07_16.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Thermal lensing is relevant in many solid-state bulk lasers and amplifiers. Here, a number of important questions on that topic are answered.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 18:45:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_07_16.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Understanding Intensity Noise</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_06_08.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is explained why the term  intensity noise is somewhat problematic in laser technology; what is actually meant, is noise of the optical power. Further, the importance of the considered range of noise frequencies is discussed. Depending on the used detector and the measurement time, you may get quite different results for the intensity noise.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 8 Jun 2018 18:04:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_06_08.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gain Saturation in Solid-state Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_05_11.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is explained how to apply the saturation intensity or saturation fluence for determining when gain saturation sets in. The example of spiking of a laser illustrates that well.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 18:36:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_05_11.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Laser Physics: the Essential Roles of Phonons in Solid-state Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_04_06.html?s=rss</link>
<description>The host medium of a laser crystal or glass does much more than just suspending the laser-active ions. In particular, phonons of the host medium often play crucial roles for laser operation.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 6 Apr 2018 09:58:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_04_06.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Dependence on Raman Conversion on the Optical Bandwidth</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_03_05.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It has been found a couple of years ago that Raman conversion in a fiber gets substantially weaker if the bandwidth of the laser light is increased from below 1 nm to several nanometers. Here, the physical reason for that is explained and illustrated with some numerical simulations.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 5 Mar 2018 17:42:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_03_05.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Self-starting of Passively Mode-locked Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_01_08.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is important to obtain reliable self-starting of passively mode-locked lasers, and thus interesting to consider phenomena which influence that. Here, we discuss the surprisingly strong influences of parasitic reflections and the benefit of using a slow saturable absorber.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 8 Jan 2018 17:52:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2018_01_08.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Energy Levels of Solid-state Gain Media</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_12_04.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Energy levels of tibial solid-stayed laser gain media are grouped in level manifolds; the article discusses some important aspects of those. In practice, that aspect does usually not force us to make laser models substantially more complicated.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 4 Dec 2017 18:17:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_12_04.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Gaussian Apertures in Resonator Models: Not Only for Exotic Lasers, But Also for Gain Guiding</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_11_02.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is shown that gain guiding effects can be taken into account in resonator design software when it supports Gaussian apertures. In some situations, the effects on the resonator modes are substantial.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 2 Nov 2017 15:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_11_02.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Importance of Spectral Wings on the Pulse Duration</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_10_03.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is well known that an optical bandpass filter can increase the duration of an ultrashort pulse. The article shows that that effect can be quite pronounced, even if the filter only attenuate the extreme spectral wings.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 3 Oct 2017 18:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_10_03.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Passive Mode Locking with Slow Saturable Absorbers: Surprisingly Stable!</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_08_31.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Some relatively simple reasoning would suggest that passively mode-locked lasers with a slow absorbers can hardly be stable - although they usually are. This article tells the history of how various explanations - partly wrong ones - have been found.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2017 11:50:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_08_31.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fiber Amplifiers: Modeling of Ultrashort Pulse Amplification with Saturation of Wavelength-dependent Gain</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_08_01.html?s=rss</link>
<description>A new algorithm has been developed for simulating the amplification of femtosecond pulses in fiber amplifiers, for example. It allows one to properly describe both the time dependence due to gain saturation and the frequency dependencies of optical fields and gain. The details have been published in the open-access journal Optics Express.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 1 Aug 2017 12:14:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_08_01.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Does a Saturable Absorber in a Laser Lead to Passive Q switching or Mode Locking?</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_04_12.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is interesting to consider what conditions are required for obtaining passive Q switching or mode locking of a laser. It turns out that the requirements for those two operation regimes are extremely different.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 12:11:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_04_12.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Interesting Features of Over-long Fiber Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_03_15.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is shown with a numerical example that choosing an overly long active fiber for a fiber laser can have quite interesting consequences: not only a reduction of the power conversion efficiency, but also strong ASE, which may even suppress laser operation.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 11:31:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_03_15.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Photonics in Times of Trouble for International Trade</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_02_17.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Photonics, being a particularly international enterprise both concerning science and industry, deadly needs that we can preserve a reasonable level of international cooperation. Unfortunately, the recent populist upheaval with attacks on cooperation and fundamental principles raises serious concerns. This article presents various thoughts on economical and political aspects to be carefully observed in order to stabilize the situation.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2017 12:44:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_02_17.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Second Opinion: a Useful Tool, also in Laser Technology!</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_01_27.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is discussed how and when a second opinion can be a useful tool in the technology area, e.g. in the development of laser devices.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 09:34:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2017_01_27.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nonlinear Input-Output Curves for Lasers</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2016_12_13.html?s=rss</link>
<description>It is explained in detail, using a numerical laser model, while the input--output curve of quasi-three-level lasers can be pronouncedly nonlinear. Effectively, one a the slope efficiency which rises for increasing pump power.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 17:22:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2016_12_13.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
<title>Challenges for Nonlinear Frequency Conversion in Extreme Wavelength Regions</title>
<link>https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2016_10_27.html?s=rss</link>
<description>Nonlinear frequency conversion is often challenging when light with extremely long or short wavelengths needs to be generated. This article discusses the many reasons for that.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 19:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
<guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.rp-photonics.com/spotlight_2016_10_27.html</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
